Amin Shirazi, PhD Student

Ames, IA

515-708-6372 | ashirazist@gmail.com | LinkedIn | Homepage | GitHub

SUMMARY

The focuses of my research are related to multiple testing of high-dimensional data when the variables are highly dependent, such as gene expression and microbiome data. Unlike other Bayesian and shrinkage methods in the literature, I exploit the dependence to propose a procedure with a more powerful test. For each of the comparisons in multiple testing, I run a linear model on the genes which are at a small distance from each other, where they are more probable to share the same information. Then proposed a test statistic that is based on the residuals of the regression model, which have a smaller standard deviation, so a higher signal-to-noise ratio is achieved. In addition, I gained broad knowledge and related technical skills in programming in R and Shiny apps. I have in total of 15 months internship experience in two different companies where I developed/contributed to multiple R package development/validation related to group sequential designs, oncology survival analysis, and designs with non-proportional hazard. Furthermore, I am the creator and maintainer of Merck Oncology Survival shiny app, a shiny app for Merck's internal survival analysis to generate multiple deliverables (Tables, listings, and figures) for regulatory submissions. I am currently a consultant in the Consulting Group at the Department of Statistics, Iowa State University, where I Provide advice to researchers about their research designs, choosing statistical methods, and interpreting statistical analysis results.

EDUCATION

Iowa State University (ISU), Ames, IA

August 2017-July 2022

Doctor of Philosophy, Ph.D., Statistics

Dissertation: Dependence Boosted Differentially Expressed Analysis

Advisor: Professor Peng Liu Cumulative GPA: 3.78/4.00

• Shahid Beheshti University (SBU), Tehran, Iran

September 2011-February 2014

Master of Science, MSc, Mathematical Statistics

Critical Component: Testing Statistical Hypothesis for Jump Models in Stochastic Differential

Equations

Advisor: Professor H.D. Hamedani Cumulative GPA: 3.70/4.00

• IKIU, Qazvin, Iran

September 2006-September 2010

Bachelor of Science, BSc, Statistics Cumulative GPA: 3.65/4.00

RESEARCH INTERESTS

 Multiple hypothesis testing, Model Assessment, Genomics and microbiome data analysis, Data Visualization, Monte Carlo (MCMC) methods, Bayesian Data Analysis, R Package Development, Shiny apps

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Department of Statistics, ISU, Ames, IA

- Performing research on statistical data analysis of microbiome and gene expressed data and specifically applying a regression-based model to multiple testing procedure to improve the test power while controlling FDR
- Characterizing a procedure to introduce a powerful test for multiple testing of dependent data by first running a linear model, and then removing false positives to control FDR
- Implementing Bayesian and shrinkage methods to compare Linear Models for Microarray Data (LIMMA) and Dependence Boosted Differentially Expressed Analysis (DBDE)

- Conducting empirical study to identify differentially expressed genes for a human breast cancer data set (GDS2250)
- Identifying differentially expressed genes in X chromosome abnormalities of cancel data using gene ontology information

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Statistical Consultant

January 2021-present

Consulting Group, Department of Statistics, ISU, Ames, IA

- Providing advice to researchers about their research designs, choosing statistical methods, interpreting statistical analysis results, use of statistical software to analyze data
- Statistical modelling for clients' research study using linear models, generalize linear models (glm's), Bayesian (JAGS, Stan) models, linear mixed effect models, etc.
- Co-author in the statistical methodology, analysis, and conclusion sections of two research papers with the clients

Biostatistics Graduate Intern

May 2021-August 2021

Merck & Co., Late Development Statistic Group, North Wales, PA

- Developing Merck & Co internal packages: Oncology Survival Analysis package (mksurv), Qualification package (mkqualify), and Merck Adaptive two-in-one Design package
- Creating and developing three shiny apps for Merck internal resources: Oncology survival analysis shiny (see gsDesign Shiny app to have an idea of what the oncology shiny I developed looks like), Statistical programming managerial dashboard for project monitoring using ggplotly, and a shiny app for adaptive two-in-one studies (for oncology trials)
- Integrating Oncology Survival Package and shiny apps to enable users to generate submissionready reports for regulatory submission purposes by downloading the results in the standard reporting format
- Contributing to developing Merck qualification package for assessing and reporting risk levels of internal packages at Merck
- Merck survival package (mksurv) development which provides standard tools for time-to-event data analysis in supporting Merck clinical studies with tools to analyze and report of Kaplan-Meier curve (including drug labeling), Restricted Mean Survival Time (RMST) analysis, Piecewise Hazard Ratio table and figure, max-combo test, etc.
- The workshop planner and coach for 'R for clinical trial analysis and reporting' workshop for the Summer 2021 Intern Program

Biostatistics Graduate Intern

September 2020-May 2021

ClinChoice, Biostatistics and Programming Division, Washington, PA

- Running simulation to compare the asymptotic results for a fixed or group sequential design under non-proportional hazard assumptions
- Package validation for Group Sequential Design packages using unit tests and snapshot tests.
 The validation included running unit tests for evaluation and record the expected output of a
 function using code. The main task was to conduct snapshot testing for deliverables (rtf
 tables, graphical outputs, and data frames) in the analysis and reporting of the group
 sequential package
- Writing R functions to generate in rtf format for Adverse Effect (AE) summary tables to be aligned with the mock tables
- Simulation studies for oncology clinical trials using smoothed hazard rate procedures (comparing bshazard and smoothHR to the internal procedure at ClinChoice)

Biostatistics Graduate Intern

June 2020-September 2020

Merck & Co., Design Methodology Division, North Wales, PA

Collaborating to package development at Merck & Co. in 3 packages: simtrial, gsDesign2 and gsdmvn

- Conducting simulation studies for fixed and group sequential designs under nonproportional hazard assumption
- Research in design methodology for group sequential designs for time-to-event endpoint trials

Data Analyst, R&D department

July 2015-July 2017

Koosha Setareh Iranian International Co, Tehran, Iran

- Implementing statistical skills to interpret market data in collaboration with sales and marketing department
- Performing generalized linear model using Beta random variables to data from market research which successfully increased sales by 15%
- Generating creative business reports, tables, charts, and graphs for the logistic department

Data Analyst, R&D department

September 2014-June 2015

Iranian Shaygan Pars, Tehran, Iran

- Interpreting sales data applying statistical models as a teamwork with sales department
- Applying Bayesian analysis using 'rstan' to provide credible intervals for the odds ratio of product sales

Statistical Consultant and Data Analyst

May 2014-September 2014

Info Tech International Company, Tehran, Iran

- Designing, conducting, and interpreting the survey analysis on the customer satisfaction of the company service
- Providing statistical consultant to the engineering and sales departments

SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT

- SHINY APPS:
 - Merck Oncology Survival Shiny app
 - Merck Programming System Tracking Dashboard (using plotly)
 - Merck Adaptive two-in-one Design shiny
 - PetFindr shiny

PACKAGE DEVELOPMENT:

- pkglite: a tool, grammar, and standard to represent and exchange R package source code as text files
- gsDesign2: non-proportional hazards and graphical multiplicity control with group sequential design
- r2rtf: an R package to create production-ready tables and figures in RTF format
- gsdmvn: simulation of fixed or group sequential design under non-proportional hazards
- simtrial: this package provides some basic routines for simulating a clinical trial
- gsDesign: the gsDesign package supports group sequential clinical trial design
- PetFindr: an R interface for the petfinder.com API (V2)

OTHER:

- Merck Oncology Analysis package
- Merck qualification package
- Merck Adaptive two-in-one package

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

INSTRUCTOR:

STAT 305, Engineering Statistics

Iowa State University

- Prepared and led lectures for both in-person and online lectures
- Wrote and graded exams

Fall 2020 - Spring 2021

- Topics included engineering data collection, descriptive statistics, elementary probability distributions, principles of experimentation, confidence intervals and significance tests, one- and two-sample studies, regression analysis, and JMP
- Approximately 70 students

TEACHING ASSISTANT:

STAT 305, Engineering Statistics Iowa State University

Summer 2019

- Statistics for engineering problem solving
 - Covering principles of engineering data collection, descriptive statistics, elementary probability distributions, principles of experimentation, confidence intervals and significance tests, one- and two-sample studies, regression analysis, and statistical software
 - Approximately 100 students

STAT 588, Statistical Theory for Research Iowa State University

Spring 2019

- Co-instructor of the course
- Helping construct tests, grading assignments, maintaining weekly office hours to communicate in person with students as needed
- Approximately 30 students

STAT 330, Probability and Statistics for Computer Science Iowa State University

Fall 2018

- Helping construct tests, grading assignments, maintaining weekly office hours to communicate in person with students as needed
- Approximately 80 students

STAT 305, Engineering Statistics

Spring 2018

Iowa State University

- Grading weekly quizzes and assignments
- Approximately 80 students

STAT 226, Introduction to Business Statistics Iowa State University

Fall 2017

- Grading assignments and exams with eight other graders to share the grading across all nine sections
- Approximately 700 students in all sections

COMPUTING SKILLS

- Working Knowledge: GitHub, Bitbucket, R, R Markdown, JMP, LATEX, SAS, Shiny, rJAGS, rStan
- Basic Knowledge: html, SPSS

PAPERS AND TECHNICAL REPORTS

- **Amin Shirazi**; Peng Liu; Yomou Qiu, Dependence Boosted Differentially Expressed Analysis (preprint)
- **Amin Shirazi**; Peng Liu; Yomou Qiu, Application of Limma in DBDE in identifying differentially expressed genes for small samples (pre-print)
- Jean Batzer; **Amin Shirazi**; Daren Mueller, Numbers of pod and seed endophyte isolates (in preparation)
- Amin Shirazi; Jane Liao; Suhas R. Sanjee, Automated Validation of Clinical Trial Analysis and Reporting Deliverables Using testthat, Phuse US Connect 2021
- Madhusudhan Ginnaram; Simiao Ye; Yalin Zhu; Yilong Zhang; Amin Shirazi, A Process to Validate Internal Developed R Package under Regulatory Environment, PharmaSUG 2021
- Mohammad Jafari; Fangwei Hou; Amin Shirazi; Mostafa Hassanalian, Determination of Experimental/Numerical Errors on Identification of Flutter Derivatives for a NACA 0020 Airfoil, AIAA SciTech Forum and Exposition (in review)

- Mohammad Jafari; Fangwei Hou; Amin Shirazi; Experimental Identification of Aeroelastic Wind Load Parameters with Uncertainty: Design of Experiment Method (in review)
- Mohammad Jafari; Fangwei Hou; Amin Shirazi, Sensitivity Analysis of Effective Parameters and Prediction of Across-wind Response of Tall Buildings in Time Domain (in review)

AWARDS AND HONORS:

Daniel H. Mowrey Graduate Consulting Awards, (Spring 2021), Iowa State University

• Awarded in recognition of outstanding contributions in the area of statistical consulting while working toward a graduate degree

Teaching excellence award (Spring 2020), Iowa State University

 Awarded in recognition of outstanding teaching of statistical courses while working toward a graduate degree

SERVICE /VOLUNTEER ACTIVITIES

Statistics in the Community, Former Treasurer and Executive Member August 2019 – present

• STATCOM at Iowa State offers statistical advice and expertise free of charge to governmental and nonprofit groups in the local community

Statistics faculty committee - student representative

August 2019 - May 2021

Department of Statistics, Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa

• Communicate relevant information from the student association to the faculty members

Iranian Students and Scholars' Association, Treasurer, ISU August 2018 - August 2019

- Event planner for 5 big events, as a teamwork, for the members of the association and non-Iranian people
- Organized the new year celebration event and hosted approximately 300 people
- Communicated with finance committee and senate of Iowa State University for funds to hold events

PROFESSIONAL ORGANIZATION MEMBERSHIP

- American Statistical Association (ASA), Institute of Mathematical Statistics (IMS)
- Iranian Statistical Society (ISS)
- * References will be provided upon request.